Guide to the Timothy Hopkins Transportation Collection M0097
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Timothy Hopkins transportation collection
1816-1942
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Hopkins, Timothy
M0097
12 Linear Feet
Scope and Content
The most significant collection of letters extant on the subject of the Central Pacific is contained in the Hopkins-Huntington correspondence. Some 2,500 letters and documents in 14 volumes cover the years 1860-1885 and are concentrated on the years 1872-1876. The letters are from Collis P. Huntington to Mark Hopkins, Leland Stanford, Alfred A. Cohen, and others. Several volumes contain correspondence between E. B. Crocker, Alfred A. Cohen, W. C. Ralston, E. E. Hewitt and Mark Hopkins.
In addition there is a volume of letters by Leland Stanford to a variety of correspondents, 1850-1893. (Transferred to University Archives).
Also in the collection are papers of Butler Ives, 1862-70, Central Pacific clipping books, 1872-92, and the papers of E. H. Miller, Jr., 1859-92.
As a part of the Hopkins manuscripts, there are numerous miscellaneous items from English and Indian railroads, 1830-1868, non-railroad transportation items, timetables, tickets, legal documents and the like.
Provenance
Gift of Timothy Hopkins, M. A. Ives, Mrs. Hazel Elizabeth Sullivan, Mrs. Carleton E. Miller, and others.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Related Materials
While this collection contains the bulk of Hopkins correspondence, as well as many early publications and printed items, the former Hopkins Transportation Library has been subdivided into several smaller collections, many of which retain the name Hopkins Transportation Collection. One may browse a list of various Hopkins-originated material here: https://searchworks.stanford.edu/catalog?q=%22Hopkins+Transportation+Library.%22&search_field=subject_terms
M0097 Timothy Hopkins Transportation Collection, 1816-1942 (12 linear feet) http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf4489n75w
M0164 Hopkins Transportation Collection, 1868-1936 (6 linear feet) http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf6j49n8tf
M0175 Hopkins Transportation Collection 1711-1959 (5 linear feet) http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf3870032v
M0200 Hopkins transportation collection, 1844-1969 (4 linear feet) http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf2z09n5zf
M0234 Hopkins Transportation Collection Photographs (3 linear feet) http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf2r29n65q
Transferred Materials
Leland Stanford correspondence has been transferred to Stanford University Archives, SC0033 Leland Stanford papers, 1840-1896 https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4085326
"R. L. Wilbur to G. T. Clark, letter of transmittal. Letters to Mark Hopkins and various correspondents, business and personal. Letters of George E. Gray to Stanford. The Stanford, Stillman, Osgood letters."
Railroads -- History; Transportation -- History.; Hopkins, Timothy; Central Pacific Railroad Company
- Series 1. ENGLAND - IRELAND
  - London and N. W. Railway, Manchester and Lincolnshire Railway reports, Jul 11, 1846 - Jun 11, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agreements between proprietors of canal navigation from Leeds to Liverpool and Northwestern Railway, etc., 1851-56 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Robert Stevenson-F. Broughton, handwritten letters, 1803-1859 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Portadown, Dungannon & Armagh Junction Railway Bill, Belfast, Hollywood & Bangor Railway Bill, 1860. 1860. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Robert Stevenson - handwritten letters (cont.) (Box 2, Folder 1a)
  - Index, dating referring to Agreements, 1845-1869 (Box 2, Folder 1b)
  - Agreements with East Lancashire Railway Corp., etc., 1847-59 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Bristol & Gloucester Railway Co. with Messrs. Stothert & Slaughter, Jun 7, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Report on Brighton Railway, etc., gradients -, 1838 (?) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Railway Clearing House - London, Apr 26, 1842-Dec 16, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Report on Mileage and Stations, etc., Belfast, Hollywood, & Bangor Railway (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Agreement between London Northwestern Railway and Lancashire & Carlisle Railway, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Ledger and drawings for aquaduct and bridge for Sheffield Canal, etc., 1816-18 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series 2. ENGLAND - INDIA - CHILE
  - Southampton, Manchester & Oxford Junction Railway (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous English railway mss. & pamphlets, especially Midland Railway (Box 4, Folder 2a)
  - Proposed railway to join London and Southampton, 1830 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Vester Railway, Report of inspection, Jan 1866. (Box 4, Folder 3a)
  - British Railway traffic statements, 1852-3 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Passenger Contract Ticket on ship Webster (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Railroad Herald Accounts Ledger (British) - [partially], 1846, 1845, 1847 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Altringham to Manchester (Mainline). (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lahore and Peshawar Railway, 1866-68. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - East Indian Railway specifications, 1854. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - East Indian Railway Subsidiary Traffic Orders, 1883. (Box 4, Folder 9a)
  - Chile (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Imperial train of the Südbahn (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Sketch of cars, undated
  - Schooners Rambler and Unity - financial records (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript (eulogy) on George Stevenson by Thomas Summerside, 1873. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Report on Northern Electric Railway. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Vallejo Electric Railway.
    - Sacramento Street Railway.
  - Sketches for construction of S.F. mole, etc. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Report of Chief Engineer on Pacific & Atlantic Railway Co., 1851 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Letters and two documents, papers of M.A. Ives. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Letters and telegrams to Butler Ives, 1862-70 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Biographical / Historical
    From Nevada Historical Society files:
    BUTLER IVES
    Born January 31st, 1830 Sheffield, Berkshire County, Massachusetts, the youngest of ten children; died December, 1872 near Vallejo, California; buried Elmwood Cemetery, Detroit, Michigan.
    Educated University of Michigan. Parents; Butler Ives and Olive Hall Morse. His ancestors, John Moss (afterwards changed to Morse) and William Ives were among Governor Eaton's party who first settled New Haven April, 1638.
    His greatest work consisted of pioneer engineering, surveying and locating the line of the Union Pacific and Central Pacific between San Francisco and Salt Lake City, working under Leland Stanford and Samuel S. Montague, chief engineer. The papers -- seventy in number -- relating to this work have been sent to the Leland Stanford University. His contract for the locating and surveying of the boundary line between the Territory of Nevada and the State of California -- running south and southeasterly from Oregon -- will be sent to the Historical Society of the State of Nevada. The Ives papers in general, running back to 1754, together with the old family bible are deposited for safekeeping with the Clarence Burton Historical Society, Detroit.
    His brother, Caleb Ives, went west on the death of Butler, December, 1872, and returned with his effects and papers. The latter were given to Marvin A. Ives by his father, Caleb, in his last days saying,
    "I want you to have Butler's papers. He was a noble man.
    The writer met about twelve years ago near Ann Arbor, Michigan an old companion, Michel J. Noyes, who had not seen Butler Ives for fifty years. His first words when I met him were,
    He was the finest man I have ever known.
    Among his effects was a letter of introduction dated December, 1862 to ___________ Miller, Banker of Sacramento, California from George A. Thayer, one of the first mayors of Grand Rapids, Michigan, who likewise spoke of him in the very highest terms, both as a gentleman and as an engineer.
    Respectfully submitted,
    signed (Marvin A. Ives)
    Ojai, California.
    May 9, 1931."
  - Four photocopies of letters, Chief Engineers Office Order book of Mrs. Mark Hopkins, 1869, 1872-3. (Box 6, Folder 2a)
  - Order book of Mrs. Mark Hopkins. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Book containing names of students using Hopkins' Library (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Ledger of Miller, Stanford, Hopkins. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Minutes of meeting of Sacramento Land Assn - (Miller gift), Apr 27, 1869. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Subscription book of Southwestern Street Railway co. [San Jose and Santa Clara], 1876 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Map - Right of way and track, Santa Rosa Branch. Napa junction to Santa Rosa (Southern Pacific Railroad). Document - Western Pacific Railroad land grant to Charles McLaughlin (signed) Leland Stanford, E. A. Miller and notarized., 10-26-1869 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series 3. CENTRAL PACIFIC MEMORABILIA
  - Book of Clippings, Funding Bill, Contains anti-Central Pacific/Stanford propaganda [cartoons, flyers, etc.], time schedules and listing of rates for fares, 1888-97. 1869.; (copies) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Book of Clippings - anti-railroad material. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Book of Clippings - as above. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Scrap book, Apr-May, newspaper accounts, reports of CPRR affairs., 1884 - (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Scrap book, newspaper accounts, reports of CPRR affairs., Jan 1885 - (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Scrap book, as above., 1884-92 - (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Scrap book, newspaper accounts, etc., 1871-83 - (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Scrap book, as above., Feb-Apr, 1884 - (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Scrap book, as above., May 1884-Jan 1886 - (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Series 4. E. H. MILLER, JR., PRIVATE LETTERS
  - Feb 1869-Jul 1873. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Aug 1873-Dec 1878. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Jan 1879-Aug 31 1882. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Sep 1882-Sep 20 1884. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Sep 25 1884-Jan 31 1887. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Feb 1887-Oct 1889. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Oct 1889-Mar 1892. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Mar 1 1892-Dec 23 1892 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Jun 21 1889 - Dec 1890, [originals]. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Dec 18 1890 - Jan 31 1892. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - E.H. Miller, Jr. Horse Book. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - E.H. Miller, Jr. Day Book, Jan 1871-Dec 1885. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - E.H. Miller, Jr. Day Book, Nov 1859-Dec 1860. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - E.H. Miller, Jr. Day Book, Nov 1859-Dec 1860. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - E.H. Miller Ledger, 1863-71 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - E.H. Miller Ledger, 1871-76 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - E.H. Miller letters, Feb. 2, 1892 - Nov. 23, 1892 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Ledger, Jan 1, 1877 - 1884 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Miller & Green Ledger, Aug 1869-77 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Brown & Miller Day Book, Jan 1877-88 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Miller & Redding Day Book, Oct 1882-87 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Deed - Central Pacific Railway Co. to John S. Hittell (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - San Lorenzo Railway Co. prospectus, 1869-71 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Virginia & Truckee Railway, 1879; (payment check). (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Central Pacific Railway - shipping ledger (oversize), Nov. 1880 (Box 14a, Folder 9)
  - Brown & Miller Day Book, Jan 1877-85. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Oak Park Ledger No. 1, owners, W.W. Brown, Miller, Montague & Arthur Brown, 1873-89 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Erie Canal Enlargement, 1851. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - E.H. Miller's check book, 1871-2 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - E.H. Miller (CPRR) taxes, 1874-95; [3 folders]. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Union Pacific Railway Co. reports, 1864-66 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Legal Brief - Huntington, Stanford, Hollister [CPRR], Apr 8, 1873. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Hyde Clark Correspondence, (Most from John Herapath). Railroad contracts, 1838-95. 1840s. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - San Francisco and San Jose Railroad timetables, 1864-68. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - California Street Cable Railroad Co. (Box 17, Folder 1a)
  - Southern Pacific Railroad, 1885-; stock certificates. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Suggestions for enlarging the scope of the hospital system of the Central Pacific and Southern Pacific Railroads, Aug 25, 1883. (Box 17, Folder 2a)
  - Union Pacific Railroad Co. Chief Engineer's Report. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Pacific and Atlantic Railroad reports, 1852 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    General note
    12) from Chief Engineer, box 5 folder 5)
  - Railroad and Locomotive Historical Society Report-Champlain & St. Lawrence Railroad. (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Scope and Contents note
    Union Tank Car (prior 1927) - history.
  - Farmers and Merchants Association for Prevention of Railway Extortion. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - US District Court [Huntington vs City of Oakland], Nov 1880 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - US District Court [Huntington vs City of Oakland], Feb 1881 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - US District Court [Huntington vs City of Oakland], Mar 1881 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Time tables, 1873 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Ship clearance papers signed by President Franklin Pierce, 1854. (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Santa Barbara Lands, (diagram and map). (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - A. C. Bassett - Southern Pacific Railroad (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Carmel-Monterey Railroad, advertisement, 1901 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Photostat of request by President Andrew Johnson for permission to build Central Pacific Railroad [piece of last tie, 1869]. (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous - passes, etc. original letter, documents and letterpress of Mark Hopkins. Three photocopies of Mark Hopkins letters, 1849. (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Timothy Hopkins' notes of railroads (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Timothy Hopkins' letters (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Yosemite Valley Railroad Co. Shares (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Shares and bonds of various railroads. (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Pahrump Valley Railroad Co. Prospectus (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - Southern Pacific Timetables (oversize rolls), 1893 and 1901.
- Series 5. HOPKINS DOCUMENTS
  - Legislative drafts, legal documents [deeds, articles of association, charters, etc.], 1861-1873 (Box 19)
    Business memoranda - billings, invoices, etc.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    v
  - Legislative drafts, case summaries, ordinances, law suit [Main vs CPRR], etc., 1860-1885 (Box 19)
    Business memoranda - inventories, etc.
- Series 6. HOPKINS CORRESPONDENCE, 1860-1885
  - HOPKINS CORRESPONDENCE index (Box 20)
    Scope and Contents
    Bound list of contents for 2 above [Hopkins Documents], 12 below [Hopkins correspondence] and Leland Stanford vol.
  - Letter of transmittal, Timothy Hopkins 1965-1871, 1923; (199 entries) (Box 20)
  - Letters of Collis P. Huntington to Mark Hopkins, Leland Stanford, and others. (Box 20)
  - Letters of C. P. Huntington to Mark Hopkins, Leland Stanford, etc. Miscellaneous documents appended - telegrams, pamphlets, clippings, etc., Jan 2, 1872 Oct 1, 1872; (197 entries) (Box 20)
  - Letters of C. P. Huntington to Mark Hopkins, Leland Stanford, and others., Oct 2, 1872 Mar 10, 1873; (187 entries) (Box 21)
  - Letters of C. P. Huntington to Mark Hopkins, Alfred A. Cohen, and others. Telegrams and miscellaneous documents appended., Mar 10, 1873; (167 entries) (Box 21)
  - Letters of C. P. Huntington to Mark Hopkins. Notice of first CPRR dividend, telegrams, newspaper clippings [the California elections] appended., Aug 26, 1873 Nov 26, 1873; (199 entries) (Box 22)
  - Letters of C. P. Huntington to Mark Hopkins, R. Franchot to Huntington., Nov 29, 1873 Apr 8, 1874; (193 entries) (Box 22)
  - Letters of C. P. Huntington to Mark Hopkins, Leland Stanford and others. Letters of I. E. Gates to Mark Hopkins., Apr 10, 1874 Jul 9, 1875; (179 entries) (Box 23)
  - Letters of I. E. Gates to Mark Hopkins. Letters of C. P. Huntington to Hopkins., Aug 25, 1875 Apr 10, 1876; (147 entries) (Box 23)
  - Letters of C. P. Huntington to Mark Hopkins. Note appended by Timothy Hopkins [entry 185] explaining conclusion of struggle between Central Pacific and Texas Pacific interests., Apr 17, 1876 Nov 26, 1886; (191 entries) (Box 24)
  - Letters of E. B. Crocker, Alfred A. Cohen, W. C. Ralston to Mark Hopkins. Telegrams, notices, miscellaneous correspondence appended., Nov 12, 1863 Oct 13, 1869; (193 entries) (Box 24)
  - Memorandum of dates of railroad construction, J. L. Wilcutt, Miscellaneous correspondence between W. C. Ralston, E. B. Crocker, Leland Stanford, Mark Hopkins, and A. A. Cohen. Copies of CP business transactions - promissory notes, drafts, etc., Oct 19, 1869 Dec 6, 1872 Mar 31, 1913.; (191 entries) (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence between Mark Hopkins, W. C. Ralston, A. A. Cohen, and others. Letters of E. E. Hewitt to Mark Hopkins. Copies of business documents, promissory notes, etc. Two letters from Timothy Hopkins to G. T. Clark. Also the deed of sale of land in Sacramento by Mary Hopkins, on, Dec 12, 1872 Jan 10, 1924 1/30/80.; (199 entries) (Box 25)